Silje Synnøve Lyder Hermansen (PhD)

(Postdoctoral fellow, PluriCourts)

Born: 22.09.1981 Telephone: +(47) 40 49 91 07

Address: Sandakerveien 22C Email: s.s.l.hermansen@jus.uio.no

0374 Oslo

Norway Web: siljehermansen.github.io

Publications:

"Building legitimacy: strategic case allocations in the Court of Justice of the European Union". *Journal of European Public Policy*. Best papers from the European Union Studies Association 2019 Biennial Conference in Denver. 1-21.

"Delegation of committee reports in the European Parliament", with Bjørn Høyland (University of Oslo) and Fang-Yi Chiou (Academie Sinica, Taiwan). *European Union Politics*. 1-22.

"Striving for influence: The effect of performance on candidate selection". *Party Politics*, 24 (4), pp 382-396

"(Self-)selection and expertise among decision-makers in the European Parliament". The Journal of Legislative Studies, 24 (1), pp 148-172

Book:

2019 *Lær deg R: En innføring i statistikkprogrammets muligheter.* Fagbokforlaget, Bergen, 224 p.

Revise and resubmit:

"Blurred Lines: The Use of Constituency-Based Assistants among Election Seekers", with Andreja Pegan (Northumbria University), submitted to European Union Politics.

Working papers:

"Will Do? Selecting Judges on Preferences and Performance", with Daniel Naurin (PluriCourts, University of Oslo)

"The sanction that isn't imposed? Roll-call voting loyalty and demotion in European Parliament elections" with Mihail Chiru (University of Oxford) and Thomas Däubler (University of Mannheim)

"How Do Legislated Gender Quotas Impact Representation?", single-authored.

"A different voice in International Courts? Gender and Judicial Behavior in Sexual and Reproductive Rights", with Malcolm Langford (University of Oslo), Daniel Naurin (University of Oslo) and Vegard Vibe (University of Oslo)

Academic background:

Positions:

05.17 – current **Assistant professor/Post. Doc.**

PluriCourts PluriCourts is a centre of excellence dedicated to the study of University of Oslo international courts.

Research area: Independence and accountability as well as judicial behavior in international courts with a special focus on the Court of Justice of the European Union.

08.11 - 01.17PhD in Political Science Department of Political Science University of Oslo

Title: «Choosing Agents: Members of the European Parliament and their Political Organizations Seen through Report Allocation» Supervisor: Bjørn Høyland

The position included 25% teaching obligations.

I had two maternity leaves during my contract: One in the winter of 2012/13 and a second in the autumn of 2015.

Summer schools

2018 School: "Methods for Computational Social Science" University of Southern California Course: Analyzing and modeling textual data (Los Angeles)

2014 School: "EITM Europe – Empirical implications of theoretical University of Mannheim models". (Mannheim)

Course: Theoretical and Methodological Foundations and Accountability and Violence

2013 School: "Parliamentary democracy in Europe" LUISS Guido Carlo School of Course: The European Parliament: Intra- and Inter-Government Institutional Politics and The Rules and Functions of the (Rome) European Parliament

2012 School: ICPSR Summer Program in Quantitative Methods of University of Michigan (Ann Arbor) Social Research

Course: Introduction to Applied Bayesian Modeling for the Social Sciences, Introduction to Game Theory and Advanced Game Theory

2011 School: Essex Summer School in Social Sciences, University of Universitetet i Essex (Essex)

Course: Single Course in Hierarchical Models

University of Oslo 03.07 - 09.08 Research assistant

Research assistance for Bjørn Høyland.

Education:

08.11 - 01.17	PhD in political science	University of Oslo
08.07 - 05.10	Master in political science	University of Oslo
08.06 - 12.06	Single courses in political science	University of Oslo
09.01 - 07.05	Bachelor in political science Consists in two years of law ("DEUG de droit") and an additional year of political science ("Licence de science politique")	Université Panthéon-Sorbonne Paris
09.98 - 07.01	Baccalauréat francais	Lycée Alain Chartier Bayeux

Honors and grants:

2019 Best Papers from the EUSA 2019 Biennial Conference

Selected as one of the best papers from the European Union Studies Association (EUSA) conference published by the Journal of European Public Policy.

2017 Writer's grant (Faqbokforlaget)

I received a grant for writing an introductory book in R (statistics program) for students in social sciences. (5000 euros)

Invited talks:

University College London (Departmental seminar, 2019)

University of Gothenburg (CJEU Database Workshop, 2019)

European Commission (Expert Meeting on the Design of a Multilateral Investment Court, 2018) University of Bergen (Bergen Exchanges on Law & Social Transformation, 2017)

University College Dublin (PADEMIA workshop on Parliamentary accountability: Assessing the link between citizens and elites in national and supranational politics, 2016)

College of Europe (PADEMIA workshop on Recent Developments in the studies of the European Parliament, 2015)

On-campus talks:

BigInsight, Norwegian Computing Center (Departmental lunch seminar, 2019)

Center for European Law (Departmental seminar, 2019)

Comparative Institutions and Regimes Seminar (Department of Political Science, 2018)

PluriCourts (Departmental seminar, 2019, 2017)

PluriCourts (Annual conference, 2018, 2019, 2020)

Conferences:

American Political Science Association (Washington DC, 2014; Boston, 2018)

European Consortium of Political science (ECPR) General Conference (Oslo, 2017; Wrocław 2019)

European Political Science Association (Barcelona, 2013; Edinburgh, 2014; Brussels, 2016; Vienna, 2018; Palfact, 2010; Factor 2020)

2018; Belfast, 2019; zoom 2020)

European Union Studies Association (Denver, 2019)

Global and Regional Governance, workshop (Stockholm, 2017)

Joint Sessions (ECPR) (Mons, 2019)

Midwest Political Science Association (Chicago, 2014; 2015)

Norwegian National Conference in Political Science (Trondheim, 2012; Tromsø, 2014; Oslo, 2015,

Stavanger 2017, Bergen 2018; Trondheim, 2019)

Standing Group on European Union (ECPR) (Hague, 2014; Trento 2016; Paris, 2018)

Standing Group on Parliaments (ECPR) (Munich, 2016)

Teaching:

Textbook: Lær deg R: En innføring I statistikkprogrammets muligheter (Introductory

book to statistical programming, 2019)

Course leader: Statistical analysis (masters/PhD level, University of Oslo, 2019, 2020)

Research methods and statistics for political scientists (bachelors level,

University College Østfold, 2013)

Profession course: Data management in R for practitioners (Course at Unit – Norwegian

Directorate for Information Technologies in Research and Higher Education,

2019)

Lectures: Research methods and statistics for political scientists (masters level,

University of Oslo, 2012, 2013, 2014)

Research methods and statistics in peace and conflict studies (masters level,

University of Oslo, 2015)

Seminar leader: EU decision-making processes and policy areas (bachelors level, University of

Oslo, 2015)

European Union institutions (bachelors level, University of Oslo, 2012) Political analysis (supervision of bachelors thesis, University of Oslo, 2012)

Quantitative methods (masters level, 2011, 2013, 2014, 2019)

Evaluation: I have also graded various theses and courses in comparative politics, political

analysis and research methods at the bachelors' and masters' level (University of Oslo, University of Bergen, University of Stavanger, University

College Østfold).

Service:

Reviewer: European Union Politics, Journal of Common Market Studies, Journal of Legislative

Studies, Journal of European Integration, Retfærd, Scandinavian Political Studies

Organizer: Panel: "Quantitative methods", Norwegian National Conference in Political Science

(Trondheim, 2019)

Departmental seminar: Department of Political Science, University of Oslo (2011-

2012)

Selection Recruitment, training and supervision of research assistant at PluriCourts (2017)

committee: Grants: "Fritt ord" student grants at the Department of Political Science (2014, 2015)

Board Department of Political Science, University of Oslo (2014-2015)

member: Department of Political Science, Université Panthéon-Sorbonne (2004-2005)

Languages:

NorwegianNative speakerRProficientFrenchProficientPythonBasicEngelskProficientLaTeX/MarkdownProficient

Other experiences:

01.11-08.11 Higher Executive Officer Ministry of Transport and

Department of Public Roads and Traffic Safety

(Section for Traffic Safety and Civil Emergency Planning)

06.08-06.09 **Editor in Chief** argument:

Argument is an interdisciplinary students' newspaper.

1998-2007 **Editorial Assistant** *Egmont Serieforlaget*

Egmont Serieforlaget - comic books.

Summer job.

2004-2016 Freelance Egmont Serieforlaget,

Part-time translator (French/Norwegian, Norwegian/French, English/Norwegian), proofreader, editor, consultant (reader's

reports).

Universitetsforlaget Forum for universitetshistorie

KUNSTforum

in Paris

Communications

02.06-06.06 **Student Intern** *Royal Norwegian Embassy*

The internship is intended to give hands-on experience with state administration to students with knowledge of French

language and society.